in this exercise we're asked to write a
function that computes and returns the
factorial of a number by using a for
loop
so the first thing i'm going to do is
declare my function and i'm just going
to call that something like factorial
and we know that we are receiving a
single argument a positive integer so
i'm just going to call that something
like n
and we're also given a number of test
cases that we can use to ensure that
this function is working properly so we
can check the answer against what we
what these factorials should be
returning once we have our logic in
place
before i do that the first thing i'm
going to do for myself is define what a
factorial is
so for any given number n a factorial of
that number is the result of multiplying
all the integers between 1 and that
number inclusive so if i have n
basically a factorial is 1 times 2 times
etc until i get to
n
now that's one way to think about it but
if i set myself up with an example and
start thinking about how i might iterate
a loop the first thing i want to think
about in when i'm iterating loop is
what's my stop condition i want to say
that n is my stop condition i could but
n is kind of an unknown at this point
i'm not sure what n is going to look
like the one thing i'm absolutely sure
of is that the factorial always ends at
1.
so if i take an example and say
something like factorial 5 factorial 5
is going to be 5 times 4 times 3 times 2
times 1.
great
now that i have that i can start
thinking about what the logic is that i
want to repeat
and looking at this i can tell that a
factorial given a certain number like 5
is basically just
accumulating the product of that number
times itself minus one
and that logic is going to lend itself
really well to a loop
the first thing i want to do in here is
initialize and declare a variable i can
use to track that product as it
accumulates as i say 5 times 4 times 3
times 2 times 1 etc
so i'm going to call that product since
we're doing multiplication here
and i'm going to initialize it to the
value 1 and i want to initialize this to
one not zero because anything multiplied
by one is itself and anything multiplied
by zero is zero which will not help me
calculate a factorial
so now i need to figure out my logic for
the loop
as i mentioned i think i'm going to go
down so i'm going to start with this
given number n so for my initializer
expression i want to initialize
something called counter
to my given number my parameter n
now i need to provide a conditional so i
want a conditional that will return true
while the loop should continue executing
and for this i think i'm just going to
say counter is greater than zero because
this will cause counter to the loop to
keep iterating while counter is greater
than zero but as soon as counter is
equal to zero it will return false and
will execute out of the loop
and then finally i'm going to decrement
counter by one each time the loop
executes so if we get something like
five first we start with five then we
subtract 1 and we get 4 down to 3 2 1
etc until counter is 0 at which point
this returns false and the loop will
stop executing
so now i need to figure out what goes in
the body of my loop
and for this i want to reassign my
accumulator value my product to
the value of product multiplied by
counter
so because product starts with one and
counter on the first iteration of the
loop will be set to n for our example
let's just say this is five for our
first iteration of the loop we're going
to reassign product to 1 times 5 which
is 5.
then we decrement counter so counter
becomes 4 and then on our next iteration
of the loop we're going to multiply
product which is 5 by 4 which will give
us 20. then we multiply 20 by 3
and that will give us 60 etcetera
etcetera until we get down to 1 at which
point we will get the final factorial of
5.
so what i want to do after i execute out
of the loop since i'm accumulating that
value with product is i want to return
the value of product
and that ought to give me my factorial
so now that i have my logic in place and
i'm feeling pretty good about that i'm
going to move to the terminal
and
run my file
and it looks like things are working out
as they should a factorial of 1 is 1
factorial of 2 is 2 factorial of 3 is 6
factorial of 4 is 24 factorial of 5 is
and then i'm just gonna go back and
check 720 50 40 40320
and as you can see those are in fact the
expected results so it looks like our
function is working